<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Popes complaint to his minion cardinals, against the good successe of the Bohemians and their generall proceedings</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114204</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849432</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849432</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14579</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14579)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1149:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Popes complaint to his minion cardinals, against the good successe of the Bohemians and their generall proceedings</title>
                  <author>Paul V, Pope, 1552-1621, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ostensibly by Pope Paul V; a verse satire.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and conjectured publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Sion College. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14579:1" rendition="simple:additions"/> THE POPES COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLAINT TO HIS MINION CARDINALS,
<hi>AGAINST THE GOOD</hi> ſucceſſe of the BOHEMIANS and their generall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
            <p>(☞)</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>Non pacem petimus ſuperi,</l>
                  <l>Date gentibus iras:</l>
                  <l>Nunc vrbes excite feras,</l>
                  <l>Coniuret in arma mundus.</l>
               </lg>
               <bibl>Lucan: Lib. 2. Pharſal:</bibl>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:14579:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14579:2"/>
            <head>☞ The Speakers Names:</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pope</hi> PAVLVS QVINTVS, <hi>A Burgheſian:</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>BVRGHESIVS</item>
                     <item>CAESARIO</item>
                     <item>ROMANO</item>
                  </list> Cardinalls.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Dominican</hi> FRYER: PASQVILL.</item>
            </list>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Strangulat incluſus dolor at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> exaeſtuat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <bibl>Ouid. triſtib: Lib. 5.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="complaint">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14579:2"/>
            <head>THE POPES COMPLAINT to his Cardinalls againſt BOHEMIA.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>POPE.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O My <hi>Caeſario!</hi> what ſhall we doe now?</l>
                  <l>Since men dare thus our Proiects diſalow:</l>
                  <l>Deride our Curſſes, and make ſlight our Power,</l>
                  <l>Scoffe at Religion, as if now the hower</l>
                  <l>Were come indeed to pull downe <hi>Babilon,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For ſo our Citie <hi>Rome</hi> they raile vpon.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They will no more our Indulgences haue,</l>
                  <l>Nor Trentals, Dirges, Maſſes, doe they craue:</l>
                  <l>They laugh at Purgatoryes flames and fire,</l>
                  <l>Deny our Merits, onely doe deſire</l>
                  <l>Saluation from the Paſſion of our Lord,</l>
                  <l>And all Our Canons are by them abhord:</l>
                  <l>To heare the <hi>Aue</hi> Bell is made a ſporte,</l>
                  <l>Vnto Confeſſion none will ſcarce reſort,</l>
                  <l>So that I feare, of Chriſtian libertines</l>
                  <l>We Atheiſts ſhall become, by outward ſignes:</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſario.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Your Holines hath tolde a grieuous tale,</l>
                  <l>Made faint my hart, my bloodles cheekes looke pale,</l>
                  <l>I quake to haue You thus affrighted bee;</l>
                  <l>And yet there is no cauſe, for ought I ſee.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14579:3"/>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>No cauſe <hi>Caeſario,</hi> why? I then begin</l>
                  <l>To tell the cauſe: what care I for their ſinne?</l>
                  <l>Or whether men in world liue ill, or well:</l>
                  <l>Or whether dying, goe to Heauen or Hell?</l>
                  <l>Whether that Princes ſwell with heat of pride,</l>
                  <l>Or doe make hatefull warres on euery ſide?</l>
                  <l>Whether whole Countries ſubjugate each other?</l>
                  <l>Deny the Faith, and all their vices ſmother?</l>
                  <l>So we doe holde Supremacie ſecure,</l>
                  <l>Haue certaine wayes our <hi>Annuals</hi> to aſſure,</l>
                  <l>Keep them in awe, that dare withſtand our Curſſe,</l>
                  <l>Bleſſing the meanes which doe enrich our Purſſe:</l>
                  <l>So we our Glory and delights maintaine,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe, what hath beene done is all in vaine.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſario.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why ſo ye doe: who dare oppoſe your Plea?</l>
                  <l>Who ſendeth not for Bleſſings to your Sea?</l>
                  <l>Who is not correſpondent to your Will,</l>
                  <l>Seeking your Holy pleaſure to fulfill?</l>
                  <l>Except ſome ſcatterd <hi>Lutherans</hi> of late,</l>
                  <l>As Malcontents for their deboiſt Eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Some ſcambling Sciſmaticks, penurious fooles,</l>
                  <l>A fewe of Hereticks in wrangling Schooles,</l>
                  <l>A common tricke of Sathans for contention,</l>
                  <l>As in all times the Church hath had diſſention:</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some few! Aye me, how can you ſay ſome fewe?</l>
                  <l>When that whole Kingdomes (as it is too true)</l>
                  <l>Haue thriued in reuolts from our deſignes,</l>
                  <l>And packing ſent our Legats and Aſſignes:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:14579:3"/>
                  <l>Who cares in <hi>England</hi> for our threates or hate?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scotland</hi> is worſſe in matters of debate,</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Ireland</hi> our Prieſts are made a pray,</l>
                  <l>The other Northerne Kingdomes keep away:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>France</hi> is our eldeſt Sonne, but what can
<hi>France</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doe gainſt him ſelfe, our Power to aduaunce?</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Netherlands</hi> Tryumph for Their rejection,</l>
                  <l>And from their natiue Princes ſeek annection</l>
                  <l>To other Soueraigntie, and ne'r againe</l>
                  <l>Will once obay, or <hi>Auſtria</hi> or <hi>Spaine:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But of all others, Curſt be that prowd Towne,</l>
                  <l>Prowd of a Fenniſh Lake to beare Vs downe:</l>
                  <l>And as they thinke, impregnable to ſtand,
<note place="margin">Geneua.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Scorne all the Forces that may come by Land:</l>
                  <l>Theſe led the Dance, and theſe doe boaſt of Time</l>
                  <l>Three hundred yeares agoe, that all their Clime,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Zwitzers, Cantons,</hi> and the <hi>Griſons</hi> haue</l>
                  <l>Sought our Religious <hi>Orgies</hi> to depraue:</l>
                  <l>And ſo by them was <hi>Wicklife</hi> taught to ſtray,</l>
                  <l>And the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> tooke the wronger way:</l>
                  <l>Then followed <hi>Hierome,</hi> and <hi>Bohemian Huſſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And other Sataniſts, who did diſcuſſe</l>
                  <l>Gainſt our good Diſcipline, and made a breach</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Germaine</hi> Factions, as their Church did teach:</l>
                  <l>So that a Prouince I can ſcarce now name,</l>
                  <l>Who as Apoſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t incurre not defame:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But neuer had the Deuill ſuch a tricke,</l>
                  <l>That ſtrooke it home, and touch't vs to the quicke:</l>
                  <l>To raiſe a Frier to withſtand a Prince!</l>
                  <l>O God how <hi>Luther</hi> dared not long ſince</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:14579:4"/> Our mightie <hi>Charles</hi> affront vnto his face,</l>
                  <l>And gainſt our Sea proclaymed all diſgrace?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But more then theſe? the <hi>Grecian</hi> Church complaines,</l>
                  <l>That they are poor, and we haue all the gaines.</l>
                  <l>They liue depreſt, wee doe vſurpe their pride,</l>
                  <l>They were the firſt, we tryumph on each ſide.</l>
                  <l>So they had rather liue in ſeruitude,</l>
                  <l>Then for the <hi>Latines</hi> any way conclude.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſario.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>If it be ſo, rowſe vp your Holineſſe,</l>
                  <l>And be the ſame you doe your ſelfe profeſſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor, both to binde and looſe,</l>
                  <l>Open the Churches Treaſure, and out-chooſe</l>
                  <l>Your Bulles, your Curſſes, Fulminations,</l>
                  <l>With all thoſe Maledicting Relations,</l>
                  <l>That haue in former times kept Kings in awe,</l>
                  <l>And made the Empire ſubiect to your Lawe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dominicke.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>With Reuerence vnto the Papacy,</l>
                  <l>(And awfull care to <hi>Peters</hi> Legacy)</l>
                  <l>Let a poor Frier open now his minde,</l>
                  <l>For well I ſee there much remaines behinde:</l>
                  <l>Alas, alas, what now will Curſſes doe?</l>
                  <l>Or Bulles, or Threatnings? If they all put to</l>
                  <l>Their helping hand, more then in former times,</l>
                  <l>To make a ſcoffe at our poor Friers Rimes?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not long agoe, we did begin with <hi>Spayne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Both Sonne and Father we thought to reſtrayne:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Charles.</hi> 5.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>But for the Father, <hi>Burbon</hi> ſack't our Cittie,</l>
                  <l>Teaching the Cloiſtred Nunnes to cry for pittie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14579:4"/> The Matrons, Virgins, wrung their hands for ruth,</l>
                  <l>To ſee ſuch rauiſhments of chaſteſt Youth,</l>
                  <l>Yea, all both ſortes and ſexes did lament</l>
                  <l>Thoſe foule outragies, to their diſcontent:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And for the Sonne durſt <hi>Aluas</hi> Duke controule,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Conclaue</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> him ſelfe, whoſe ſoule
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Phillip.</hi> 2.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>He baited, hunted with ſtrong inference</l>
                  <l>Of Paſtorall duties, and more conſequence</l>
                  <l>Of humane clemency, religious Zeale,</l>
                  <l>Humbled regard, and after did appeale</l>
                  <l>To Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe againſt that Curſſe,</l>
                  <l>That made the Armies, and the Cauſe the worſſe:</l>
                  <l>And this was all wee got by our fine skill;</l>
                  <l>Which they call Tyrannie, as others will</l>
                  <l>Diſclaime the like: For when our Father had</l>
                  <l>That Prince of Princes, ſo reputed bad,</l>
                  <l>That great <hi>Elizaheth</hi> out of the Church</l>
                  <l>With Menaces caſt, we fell in the Lurch:</l>
                  <l>She as a Rocke immoueable did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>And all our Prieſts were hated in her Land:</l>
                  <l>Yea, other Princes from their ſtrong Allyance,</l>
                  <l>Prepared to withſtand our ſtrange defiance.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come nearer home! what did our Threatning worke,</l>
                  <l>But rowſe the ſleeping Lyon, who did lurke</l>
                  <l>Cowchant before, and by St. <hi>Mark</hi> his Charme</l>
                  <l>Reſolued was to doe vs no great harme:</l>
                  <l>But when we would not ſo appeaſed ſtand,</l>
                  <l>He Panther-like opened his ſtronger hand,</l>
                  <l>And ſhewed his Tallents, when within his reach,</l>
                  <l>The Prey was come: ſo <hi>Venice</hi> made a breach</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14579:5"/> Againſt our Walles: Yea, hilly
<hi>Sauoy</hi> dare</l>
                  <l>To counterchecke our Diſcipline not ſpare,</l>
                  <l>And therefore ſure when we are thus withſtood,</l>
                  <l>Theſe Bulles and Fulminations doe no good:</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Burgheſius.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then doe as <hi>Peters</hi> viſion biddeth vs,</l>
                  <l>Both kill and eate, what need we more diſcuſſe?</l>
                  <l>If manſuetude cannot confirme our Sate,</l>
                  <l>Let ſlaughters on each ſide quench the debate:</l>
                  <l>Some, either loue or money will perſwade;</l>
                  <l>Or hope of Bliſſe, ſuch Tyrants to inuade:</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dominick.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O ſay not ſo; this makes vs odious,</l>
                  <l>And is againſt Religion dangerous:</l>
                  <l>Looke into holy Writ, and you ſhall finde,</l>
                  <l>How Regicides haue ſtill bene caſt behinde,</l>
                  <l>The Captaines, that kild <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi> were ſlaine,</l>
                  <l>And he which fell on <hi>Saul,</hi> lyed all in vaine:</l>
                  <l>Thus of the reſt: But come to later times,</l>
                  <l>Was not ſtout <hi>Naſſaus</hi> murthers counted Crimes?
<note place="margin">Prince of <hi>Orenge.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Reueng'd with puniſhment, abhor'd with hate,</l>
                  <l>And made a cauſe of malice, and debate?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <lg>
               <l>What got we by thoſe <hi>Henries</hi> of <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Kild by our <hi>Iacobines,</hi> whome to aduance</l>
               <l>With Saint-like honour, <hi>Rome</hi> did nothing ſpare?</l>
               <l>But then alas, the Princes did declare</l>
               <l>Vpon the ſame, our enemies profeſt:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Hugonites</hi> grewe ſtrong, and did deteſt</l>
               <l>Such crueltie, yea with Inuectiues durſt</l>
               <l>For that foule Sinne; holde <hi>Rome</hi> herſelfe accurſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14579:5"/> And as for <hi>England,</hi> as of late was ſeene,</l>
               <l>The ſtrange Attempts againſt that peereleſſe Queene</l>
               <l>(For ſo I needs muſt ſay, how e're wee know</l>
               <l>Shee was ſeduced another way to goe:)</l>
               <l>Affected with Remorſe, ſuch as ſo wrought,</l>
               <l>That Catholickes themſelues, e'ill of Vs thought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But when I once the Powder Treaſon name,</l>
               <l>I doe proteſt, I tremble at the ſame,</l>
               <l>And muſt confeſſe the Deuill diſappointed,</l>
               <l>By ſuch a Stratagem 'gainſt Gods annoynted.</l>
               <l>For how ſo ere Kings in Religion faile;</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Cyrus</hi> is Gods ſeruant to preuaile</l>
               <l>In his deſignes, and they Vicegerents are</l>
               <l>For good or bad, to manage all his warre:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay come to Fryer <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Venice</hi> State,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Life ſo many wayes was ſought of late:</l>
               <l>It makes me thinke vpon the ſtubborne <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who <hi>Paules</hi> good Doctrine did ſo much refuſe,</l>
               <l>That Vowes were made to kill him in the way,</l>
               <l>But he preuented them: Thus, thus I ſay</l>
               <l>To kill will doe no good, but cauſe the Foe</l>
               <l>More ſtronger with an armed Guard to goe,</l>
               <l>And raiſe a Scandall on your Fatherhood,</l>
               <l>Tearming the Cardinalls the Serpents broode,</l>
               <l>That haue no better meanes the Truth to teach,</l>
               <l>But Leſſons of foule Murther ſtill doe Preach:</l>
            </lg>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Romano.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then let vs doe as <hi>Machabans</hi> did,</l>
                  <l>When the poore <hi>Iewes</hi> were in the Mountaines hid,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14579:6"/> For feare of proude <hi>Antiochas:</hi> take Armes,</l>
                  <l>Rowſe vp our Courages with warlike charmes,</l>
                  <l>Summon our Friends, open our Treaſures ſtore:</l>
                  <l>Aduance the Churches Standard, and before</l>
                  <l>The Armies Catholicke with Bleſſings goe,</l>
                  <l>Theſe Caitiffe Heretickes to ouerthrow.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dominick.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>This ſauors better then the former twaine,</l>
                  <l>For this is Manly, Princely: Yet againe</l>
                  <l>How ſhall wee thus preuailingly proceed,</l>
                  <l>When our own Countries are not well agreed?</l>
                  <l>It is not now, as when our <hi>Innocent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did treade vpon the Dragon, and was bent</l>
                  <l>To ſommon <hi>Fredericke</hi> to <hi>Romes</hi> high Throne,</l>
                  <l>Where that that his Holineſſe as on a Stone,</l>
                  <l>Did ſet his Foote vpon the Emperors necke,</l>
                  <l>The proudeſt Monarchies to counterchecke!</l>
                  <l>It is not now, as when three Dayes together,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the Third (though <hi>Caeſar)</hi> in foule weather</l>
                  <l>Did Bare-leg wayte with his Empreſſe and Sonne,</l>
                  <l>Eu'n at your Pallace Gate: Men then begun</l>
                  <l>To reuerence the Church, and durſt not ſtray,</l>
                  <l>From true Religion the wronger way:</l>
                  <l>It is not now, as when our <hi>Pandulph</hi> came</l>
                  <l>To Englands <hi>Iohn,</hi> and taught him a ſtrange Game</l>
                  <l>Of poore Submiſſion, leaſt French <hi>Lewis</hi> might,</l>
                  <l>Diſmiſſe him of his Dignity, and Right!</l>
                  <l>It is not now, as when <hi>Henry</hi> the Fift.</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Germane</hi> Prince, his Father durſt out Lift</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14579:6"/> From the Imperiall Seate at your beheſt,</l>
                  <l>And raiſd ſuch Armies, when you did requeſt!</l>
                  <l>It is not now, as when that you Deuiſde</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Millaine, Naples,</hi> and great State premiſde</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> ſo deare to
<hi>Peters</hi> Chaire,</l>
                  <l>So Louing, Carefull, True, and Debonaire;</l>
                  <l>That hee brought downe his Troopes to Vs amaine,</l>
                  <l>And ſurely ment the Empire to regaine,</l>
                  <l>When of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> hee was Crown'd</l>
                  <l>Chiefe Emperor, and ſo moſt Warlike found</l>
                  <l>Againſt your then ſuppoſed Foe: Vntill</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Pauies</hi> Battaile wrought a fatall ill!</l>
                  <l>It is not now, as when the Prieſts and Friers,</l>
                  <l>Stucke to their Beades with limited Deſires,</l>
                  <l>And went no further then a motion,</l>
                  <l>To ſtirre vp men to true Deuotion,</l>
                  <l>Were not tranſcendent in their Practiſes,</l>
                  <l>Nor paſt themſelues in Forraine extacies:</l>
                  <l>For on my Soule, If euer <hi>Rome</hi> had croſſe,</l>
                  <l>Or Subject muſt bee vnto greater loſſe:</l>
                  <l>It is the ſtirring <hi>Ieſuites</hi> that wrought it,</l>
                  <l>And they as Clergy polliticks haue ſought it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Good GOD what hath Religion to doe</l>
                  <l>But with Religion, men to ſtirre and wooe</l>
                  <l>To Holy duties, Sanctitie of Life,</l>
                  <l>Pennance for ſinne, to Cure debates and ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>To ſaue the Soules of ſuch as goe aſtray</l>
                  <l>Like ſilly Ignorants the wronger way.</l>
                  <l>So that I know not, as the Caſe now ſtands,</l>
                  <l>But Miſchiefe is on foote in Chriſtian Lands:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14579:7"/> And to my feare I ſpeake when you make tryall,</l>
                  <l>The end will bee our Scorne, or worſe Denyall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You ſend to <hi>Albert,</hi> as a Grandſires Sonne,</l>
                  <l>Not doubting but an Vnckles name hath wonne</l>
                  <l>Much of regard: An anſwer ſoone is made,</l>
                  <l>Hee Liues and Dyes vnder the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> ſhade,</l>
                  <l>But 'las for him! Theſe Flemmiſh Burgers range</l>
                  <l>As farre as <hi>Cleue,</hi> and ſtand in euery Grange,</l>
                  <l>Strong in their Courts of Guard, and will not yeeld</l>
                  <l>To giue him way in any Towne, or Field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You ſend to <hi>France,</hi> why <hi>France</hi> is ſcarſe her owne,</l>
                  <l>The Proteſtants then Catholickes are growne</l>
                  <l>More ſtrong, and ſuch are their Great Princes Power,</l>
                  <l>That no man knowes againſt them at this hower</l>
                  <l>Who may preuaile: but onely this is plaine,</l>
                  <l>They cannot ſpare a man to goe in vaine:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You ſend to <hi>Phillip</hi> Catholicke, and Sonne,</l>
                  <l>Who hath ſo many Crownes, &amp; Countries wonne,</l>
                  <l>But how ſhall they be kept on Head ſecure</l>
                  <l>Without great force? and how ſhall he endure</l>
                  <l>To raiſe a forraine Army for your ſake,</l>
                  <l>That was compeld a ſodaine Peace to make</l>
                  <l>With your worſt friends? Expect not ayde from thence</l>
                  <l>Sufficiently to further your pretence:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>You ſend to <hi>Pole,</hi> hath <hi>Pole</hi> no Warres in hand</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Turkes,</hi> with <hi>Swenes,</hi> or with the neighbour Land?</l>
                  <l>And are you ſure the Paſſages are free,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sileſia's</hi> Gates, and Countries opened bee?</l>
                  <l>Is not <hi>Luſatia</hi> ſhut, <hi>Morania</hi> gon,</l>
                  <l>And how can <hi>Poles</hi> reliefe bee hoped on?</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:14579:7"/> Except ſome ſtragling
<hi>Coſacks</hi> heere and there,</l>
                  <l>As of all Nations you the like may heare:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As for the <hi>Cantons, Swiſſe,</hi> and
<hi>Griſans</hi> ſtout,</l>
                  <l>It is but folly for to goe about</l>
                  <l>Their ſuccor's more then Mercenary pay,</l>
                  <l>And ſo to either ſide they make their way:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I neede not name your Principates about yee,</l>
                  <l>Nor other Prouinces that are without yee,</l>
                  <l>Of whome ſome watch the <hi>Turke,</hi> ſome are at jarre</l>
                  <l>Amongſt themſelues, ſome for to raiſe a Warre</l>
                  <l>Haue little meanes, leſſe men, and leſſer minde,</l>
                  <l>And ſo muſt prooue vnto your Sea vnkinde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But in a worde, the Princes are ſo ſtrong</l>
                  <l>Of this laſt Vnion, that the meaneſt Wrong</l>
                  <l>Done vnto one, is done vnto another,</l>
                  <l>A Brother cannot better loue a Brother.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then it ſhould ſeeme, wee ſhall let all alone,</l>
                  <l>And ſigh, and weepe, and crye, lament and grone:</l>
                  <l>Pule at this outrage, kiſſe the ſcourging Rod,</l>
                  <l>And onely like a Childe, crye out O GOD!</l>
                  <l>Giue way to Rumor, and with Patience,</l>
                  <l>Beare the report of Shame with feeling ſence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>One day doth bring vs newes, that <hi>Bohem</hi> Dare</l>
                  <l>Againſt their Emperour themſelues declare;</l>
                  <l>Rejecting <hi>Auſtria,</hi> as it were in ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>Forſaking Vs, as if wee were forlorne:</l>
                  <l>Another Day reportes, the <hi>Palatine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With other <hi>Lutherans</hi> a League combine</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14579:8"/> That traytorlike haue Crowned him a King</l>
                  <l>Againſt his Soueraigne, and Encomions ſing</l>
                  <l>For many good ſucceſſes, as they thriue</l>
                  <l>In warlike Stratagems, and doe contriue</l>
                  <l>To raiſe more Forces, ſend abroad to Friends,</l>
                  <l>Propoſing ſtranger thinges for ſtranger ends.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bohemia</hi> has a Prince borne in the Towne,</l>
                  <l>The Warres preuaile, their Foes are beaten downe,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Ferdinand</hi> doth Droope, <hi>Vienna</hi> ſtandes</l>
                  <l>As in a maze, folding their Armes and handes.</l>
                  <l>The people throng in heapes and flocke a pace,</l>
                  <l>In euery Towne, to hearken our Diſgrace:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bucquoy</hi> is beaten, and <hi>Dampire</hi> is fled,</l>
                  <l>the <hi>Poliſh Coſſacks</hi> they are ſlaine and Dead:</l>
                  <l>The Troopes are ouercome, and in the Field</l>
                  <l>Two thouſand loſt, Foure hundred they did yeeld,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Anholt</hi> and <hi>Mansfuld,</hi> had a glorious Day,</l>
                  <l>Beſides reuolters, who ſtill runne away,</l>
                  <l>And leaue their Prince to ſerue a Strangers turne,</l>
                  <l>Oh that conſuming Fier might them burne!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But heer's not all: for now to Vexe vs more,</l>
                  <l>Then either they, or Wee thought of before,</l>
                  <l>They looke for Ayde from <hi>Brittaine,</hi> Horſe and Foote,</l>
                  <l>With vnbeleeued Sommes of Golde to boote:</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>London</hi> Heretickes of their free Guift,</l>
                  <l>For to disburſe with Largenes haue made ſhift:</l>
                  <l>Nay when they heare Religion is the Cauſe,</l>
                  <l>They flocke amaine without or ſtop or pauſe:</l>
                  <l>But when they talke of <hi>Romes</hi> great ouerthrow?</l>
                  <l>They clap their handes for Ioy, and ſo doe ſhow</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:14579:8"/> Their Hate to Vs, wiſhing no other Warre</l>
                  <l>Nor recompence for all their Coyne: Thus farre,</l>
                  <l>Theſe heauy headed Dutch haue wrought their ends,</l>
                  <l>And doe increaſe, as wee decay in Friends.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſario.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then I perceiue it needes muſt end with blowes,</l>
                  <l>And if ſucceſſe attend: Our Lady knowes</l>
                  <l>To what a mountaine of foule Prodegies,</l>
                  <l>Their Pride may riſe to with their Victories.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But are you ſure the Emperor hath ſent</l>
                  <l>For ſuccour into <hi>Spaine,</hi> as it was ment,</l>
                  <l>Rather to breake off Peace &amp; Leagues with all,</l>
                  <l>Then ſee the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Diadem to fall,</l>
                  <l>And this me thinkes your Holineſſe might moue</l>
                  <l>By ſpeciall Embaſſy, and ſo reproue</l>
                  <l>Their great retardance, which hath giuen them leaue</l>
                  <l>Refractary to growe, as I conceiue:</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dominicke.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then you conceiue amiſſe, nor are you wiſe,</l>
                  <l>To make your Paſſion author of aduiſe,</l>
                  <l>Greateſt Deſignes attend on Circumſtance,</l>
                  <l>And ſauerie Pollicie muſt them Aduance:</l>
                  <l>For if hee ſtart from <hi>England,</hi> as it ſtands,</l>
                  <l>Or breake the League with <hi>Hollands</hi> Netherlands,</l>
                  <l>How can Hee all theſe turnes ſupply together,</l>
                  <l>Or keepe his Nauy ſafe, from raging weather?</l>
                  <l>Whereas to temporiſe and to renue</l>
                  <l>A ſtronger League by Peace, this may enſue,</l>
                  <l>That all thoſe Forces, which hee well can ſpare</l>
                  <l>With ſo much Treaſure, as his Princely care</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:14579:9"/> May husband for this purpoſe, ſhall be ſent</l>
                  <l>Vnto th' Imperiall Townes incontinent:</l>
                  <l>Then with ſome more Security they may</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Naples, Millaine, Sicell,</hi> March away</l>
                  <l>Thoſe trayned Gariſons, filling their roomes</l>
                  <l>With other <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and new come Groomes:</l>
                  <l>Yet take you heede, this can but once bee done,</l>
                  <l>And that's well ended, which is well begun:</l>
                  <l>But marke their Paſſages ſo hard to finde,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Swiſſe</hi> and <hi>Griſons</hi> proue to them vnkinde:</l>
                  <l>(For if your Holines wiſh for a Brother,</l>
                  <l>No way but this: You cannot name another)</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Millaine</hi> to <hi>Vienna</hi> muſt they goe,</l>
                  <l>Ouer fiue Mountaines full of Ice and Snowe,</l>
                  <l>And in the Summer, which is ſtrange to tell,</l>
                  <l>It is not for their Marches halfe ſo well:</l>
                  <l>Yet in extreames there is no remedy,</l>
                  <l>Patience beares out the greateſt extacy.</l>
                  <l>Well let them goe, health and good Spirits guide them,</l>
                  <l>And all the Saincts of Heauen goe beſide them:</l>
                  <l>For I am ſure, whether they March or Troope,</l>
                  <l>The third man in the Trauaile needs muſt Droope.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Burgheſius.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then holy Sir your Legate ſend to <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who cannot but this Cauſe as much Aduance,</l>
                  <l>Or rather more: For <hi>France</hi> is eldeſt Sonne</l>
                  <l>Vnto our <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſhould with eaſe bee wonne.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dominick.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Are you a <hi>Conclauiſt,</hi> and know no more,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>France</hi> her State? you might haue heard before</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14579:9"/> That <hi>Condyes</hi> Prince, and others of eſteeme,</l>
                  <l>Would with their bloods Religion redeeme;</l>
                  <l>And ſtand 'gainſt all Edicts vpon their Guard,</l>
                  <l>Hoping at laſt to haue a good award:</l>
                  <l>Yet for all this hath <hi>Ferdinando</hi> Writ,</l>
                  <l>(How euer <hi>Bolloigne</hi> did miſlike of it:)</l>
                  <l>That ſome Commaunder might him Forces bring,</l>
                  <l>With loue and liking of the youthfull King,</l>
                  <l>Nor did hee thus, as barely, without charge:</l>
                  <l>But in good Tearmes declare his minde at Large.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt Noble Prince remember <hi>Charles</hi> the Great
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Supported <hi>Rome,</hi> and got th' Imperiall Seate:</l>
                  <l>As of the Church only Protector cal'd,</l>
                  <l>Which was by <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Saraceus</hi> enthral'd,</l>
                  <l>And thereupon is <hi>France</hi> the eldeſt Sonne,</l>
                  <l>And for true valour hath ſuch honour wonne:</l>
                  <l>Then be not now to Catholicks vnkinde,</l>
                  <l>But let vs your Reliefe as Princely finde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A ſecond Inference he had from Blood, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which ſeem'd amongſt the Statiſts neer as good:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Emperour</hi> was Vncle to the <hi>Queene,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As may within the Records well be ſeene:</l>
                  <l>This he enforſt from bond of Amitie,</l>
                  <l>Ariſing out of Conſanguinitie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A third was Morall, from protection <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of other Princes in rejection,</l>
                  <l>Oh for to help diſtreſſed, is a glory,</l>
                  <l>As you may read in many an ancient Story.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The fourth had ground vpon good Policie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of iuſt reuenge to ſcourge iniquitie:</l>
                  <l>Reuolts I meane, and diſobedience</l>
                  <l>To lawfull Kings, from a ſtrong inference</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14579:10"/> Of Treaſon in their ſoule enormous Crimes,</l>
                  <l>As hath appeared in all moderne Times:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The fift was taken from a Holy feare,</l>
                  <l>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Leaſt that the <hi>Turke</hi> might of theſe troubles heare,</l>
                  <l>And ſo the youth of <hi>Othoman</hi> awake,</l>
                  <l>Aduantages of our Diſtreſſe to take,</l>
                  <l>And then no doubt they might repent too late,</l>
                  <l>That e're they durſt the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> houſe amate.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Burgheſius.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And was not this well Vrg'd? nay was it not</l>
                  <l>A preſident for Princes to haue got,</l>
                  <l>Of excitation 'gainſt ſo great a Foe,</l>
                  <l>That ſure will worke more miſchiefe and more woe?</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Poland</hi> heard of this, or <hi>Ruſſis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If <hi>Denmarke, Pomeran,</hi> and <hi>Perſia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If Triple Crowned <hi>Brittaine</hi> knew it ſure,</l>
                  <l>Hee would the ſame as forcible endure:</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Venice, Sauoy, Florence,</hi> and the reſt</l>
                  <l>Were taught this Leſſon, they would count it beſt:</l>
                  <l>Yea eu'n the <hi>Cantons</hi> and the Snowy
<hi>Vales,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Could not repute it as ſome olde wiues Tales:</l>
                  <l>But for the Good of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Nations,</l>
                  <l>The League make ſtrong by Combinations.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dominick.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>I doe confeſſe it hath ſome outward ſhow</l>
                  <l>Of a preualent Reaſon: But on to goe</l>
                  <l>The dogged Duke of <hi>Bolloigne,</hi> as I heare</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Burbon</hi> and the reſt a Dangerous Peere,</l>
                  <l>Hath anſwerd all: Retorting Argument</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Auſtria,</hi> thus of greater Conſequent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Touching the Firſt: <hi>Religion</hi> is no Plea!
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> did ſo affect our Sea:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14579:10"/> But eu'n the <hi>Catholicks</hi> of beſt eſteeme,</l>
                  <l>Were ſtill enforſt their Freedomes to redeeme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Affrighted were with Cruelties, and Pride</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Auſtrias</hi> houſe extended on each ſide,</l>
                  <l>Found Great <hi>Mathias</hi> ſterne, this man too heady,</l>
                  <l>Vnconſtant, Cruell, and in Truth vnſteady:</l>
                  <l>And now they liue vnder this Noueliſt</l>
                  <l>More quiet farre, as doing what they liſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſecond with like reaſon Anſwer had: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>The greateſt Monarchies (though ne'r ſo bad)</l>
                  <l>Were Fathers of their Kingdomes, and to looke</l>
                  <l>Vnto their Subjects Peace, which they forſooke</l>
                  <l>As Tyrants, if they brought them to a Warre</l>
                  <l>Againſt their willes, of perill, or too farre:</l>
                  <l>And how could <hi>France</hi> dilacerate her State;</l>
                  <l>Empty her Treaſure at ſo great a rate,</l>
                  <l>Send Forces to a Forraine Prince, and leaue</l>
                  <l>Her Natiue children? This were to bereaue</l>
                  <l>Them of their deareſt Liues: For why at home,</l>
                  <l>Miſchiefe enough in euery Towne did rome.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beſides, vnto <hi>Bohemias</hi> King there is</l>
                  <l>So great Allyance, if I doe not miſſe,</l>
                  <l>That neuer Prince in any Age had more,</l>
                  <l>Nor could Catalogue ſuch a Role before:</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Brittaine</hi> by his Daughter calls him Sonne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>Norway</hi> on his ſide are wonne:</l>
                  <l>The one an Vnckle, as is <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> knowne,</l>
                  <l>The other as a Friend with <hi>Sweden</hi> growne:</l>
                  <l>The Prince of <hi>Orenge</hi> is ſo neere in Blood,</l>
                  <l>That I am ſure hee'le doe him any good.</l>
                  <l>His other Kindred come from <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With many a Count and Duke of <hi>Wittenburgh,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14579:11"/> I name not <hi>Bolloigne,</hi> nor Confederates</l>
                  <l>With many Princes in their beſt eſtates,</l>
                  <l>Nor doe I twenty Prouinces recite,</l>
                  <l>With all their Lords of full ſufficient might,</l>
                  <l>Who are his owne: ſo that (if Reaſon yield)</l>
                  <l>They muſt be drawne into the bloody Field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As for the third, the matter that doth driue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Mill, doth drowne it<hi>:</hi> For if you contriue</l>
                  <l>The Argument from former charitie,</l>
                  <l>Or Lawes of Nations louing amitie,</l>
                  <l>To ayde diſtreſſed Princes: then hath
<hi>France</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Farre leſſe to doe the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> to aduance,</l>
                  <l>Then help the <hi>Palatine:</hi> For who knowes not,</l>
                  <l>When they had newes of both our <hi>Henries</hi> got</l>
                  <l>And of their murthers, they did laugh out right,</l>
                  <l>As if they meant remonſtrance of deſpight:</l>
                  <l>And when Duke <hi>Neuers</hi> to <hi>Mathias</hi> went,</l>
                  <l>They with a ſcornfull Anſwer home him ſent,</l>
                  <l>Bidding yong <hi>Lewis</hi> looke himſelfe about him,</l>
                  <l>And no way meddle with the thinges without him:</l>
                  <l>For why, the Meſſage had relation</l>
                  <l>Vnto the concord of each Nation?</l>
                  <l>As for the <hi>Palatine,</hi> he friendly ſtood,</l>
                  <l>And with great ſommes of Money did them good:</l>
                  <l>Therfore if that the ſuccourleſſe haue aide,</l>
                  <l>To help <hi>Bohemia</hi> they are well appaide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The fourth did no way faſten well together, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  </l>
                  <l>For Treaſon or reuolts (euen chooſe you whether)</l>
                  <l>Were different in States Electiue, and</l>
                  <l>Such as by Claime of Heritance did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Nor was the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> houſe enfeoft ſo ſure</l>
                  <l>Vnto the Empire, but it might endure</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14579:11"/> Fraction of nombers: As for Preſident,</l>
                  <l>They haue example of great conſequent:</l>
                  <l>Firſt <hi>France</hi> the Weſterne Monarchy poſſeſt,</l>
                  <l>How e're the <hi>Germans</hi> could it not digeſt:</l>
                  <l>Then they contriu'd a ſtrong Election</l>
                  <l>Conditionall in the reiection:</l>
                  <l>Nor is it Newes an Emperour to haue,</l>
                  <l>From other <hi>German</hi> Princes layde in Graue,</l>
                  <l>And ſo hath <hi>Hungar</hi> and <hi>Bohemia</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had Kings at once, though not of <hi>Auſtria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And therefore this had pooreſt Inference,</l>
                  <l>As hauing to that Crowne a reference;</l>
                  <l>So that to name Reuolts in ſuch a caſe</l>
                  <l>Vpon the ſcanning would the cauſe Diſgrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As for an Interceding, which they bring,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Ferdinand</hi> was choſen once their King,</l>
                  <l>Compulſion they doe Anſwer is no Lawe,</l>
                  <l>And then the Faction kept them all in awe:</l>
                  <l>So that it was not orderly contriu'd,</l>
                  <l>But ſoone Reuerſde by ſuch, as now ſuruiu'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The laſt was weakeſt of them all: The <hi>Turke</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would by this meanes all <hi>Europe</hi> ſet on worke:</l>
                  <l>Nay ſaide the <hi>Bolloigne</hi> Duke, if it bee ſo,</l>
                  <l>There is no ſence againſt the King to goe.</l>
                  <l>For then the Warres muſt needs protracted bee,</l>
                  <l>And greater troubles wee ſhall dayly ſee:</l>
                  <l>The onely way our ſtrength for to Increaſe,</l>
                  <l>Is for the Emperor to aske a Peace,</l>
                  <l>And with the King of <hi>Boheme</hi> to Combine</l>
                  <l>A League of amitie, or elſe reſigne,</l>
                  <l>As from the Firſt, vnto Election</l>
                  <l>Of the Seauen Princes, whoſe connection</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14579:12"/> May well, if all State matters ſo diſpoſe,</l>
                  <l>As perfect Friends be made of greateſt Foes:</l>
                  <l>Thus writ the Duke, and ſauour how it liſt,</l>
                  <l>How er'e your Holines may thinke he miſt,</l>
                  <l>As not acquainting <hi>Rome</hi> with theſe euents,</l>
                  <l>Yet wrought it to the People great contents.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Romano.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Rather then thus: euen I my ſelfe will goe</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Turke</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> for their farther woe:</l>
                  <l>What, ſhall our Father and the Church ſubmit</l>
                  <l>To Traiterous Heretickes? Wee'l none of it:</l>
                  <l>But raiſe vp Strangers to defend our cauſe,</l>
                  <l>To vnderſtand our Canons and our Lawes,</l>
                  <l>To breake the necke of contumacious pride,</l>
                  <l>And whip theſe drunken Sciſmaticks beſide:</l>
                  <l>And if the <hi>Goths</hi> were cal'd The Scourge of God,</l>
                  <l>Wee'l bruiſe them with a <hi>Mahumetan</hi> Rod.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dominick.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come, this is frency and no policy,</l>
                  <l>No Zeale, religion, nor morallity:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe a finger akes, we therefore cut</l>
                  <l>The whole hand off, and ſo ſtill fooliſh, put</l>
                  <l>The body vnto cauteriſing paine,</l>
                  <l>As hauing greater cauſe ſtill to complaine:</l>
                  <l>For thus haue Kingdomes loſt their ſiberty,</l>
                  <l>And ſubiect bene vnto captiuity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Britaine</hi> for ſuccour ſundry Nations cal'd,</l>
                  <l>VVho in their ſeueral times their freedomes thral'd,</l>
                  <l>The barb'rous <hi>Iriſh</hi> went for <hi>Dermonds</hi> Rape</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Englands</hi> King, and ſo they did not ſcape<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>Grecian</hi> Empire called Strangers in,</l>
                  <l>VVho preſently did all their Countries win:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14579:12"/> Yea <hi>Spayne</hi> hath felt the like, when <hi>Iulian</hi> Count,</l>
                  <l>In recconing vp diſgraces, did ſurmount</l>
                  <l>In his reuenge about his Daughters croſſe,</l>
                  <l>When by the <hi>Mores</hi> it had ſo great a loſſe.</l>
                  <l>And this will be the end of <hi>Turkiſh</hi> aide,</l>
                  <l>Nay, in my ſoule I further am affraide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>That <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall feele their tyranny farre worſſe</l>
                  <l>Then any Warre, or Hereticks foule curſſe.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet ſomthing muſt be done; ſhall we giue way</l>
                  <l>To all theſe Treaſons, and not once aſſay</l>
                  <l>To adde a Cataplaſme vnto this wound,</l>
                  <l>Which will the body of the Church confound?</l>
                  <l>Shall we let <hi>Ferdinand</hi> be thus abuſed,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Spayne</hi> diſpis'd, when <hi>Auſtria</hi> is refuſed?</l>
                  <l>No ſure, if God help not, the Deuill muſt,</l>
                  <l>If euer man, or skill, or Arte did truſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dominicke.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>O ſay not ſo, your Holines may take</l>
                  <l>A calmer courſe, and all extreames forſake:</l>
                  <l>Diſmiſſe the bloudy <hi>Ieſaits</hi> from hence,</l>
                  <l>With all ſtrange Projects doe your ſelfe diſpence,</l>
                  <l>Abſtaine from murthers, cruelties and rage,</l>
                  <l>Doe not the Church exotickly engage,</l>
                  <l>But ſend abroad ſome holy Prieſts of Name,</l>
                  <l>Who may with quietnes diſcourſe their blame,</l>
                  <l>Diſpute with reaſon, and religious care,</l>
                  <l>Teach them, of foule Damnation to beware,</l>
                  <l>Plead out for Conſcience, and true loue of God,</l>
                  <l>Who elſe will whip them with a ſcourging Rod:</l>
                  <l>Vrge their obedience vnto Kings of worth,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Gouernment ſuch proffit bringeth forth</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14579:13"/> Of Peace and Plenty, that what e're befall,</l>
                  <l>They doe Religious Zeale profeſſe in all:</l>
                  <l>O 'tis a comfort, When that men be wrought</l>
                  <l>By gentlenes to God, and ſo are taught</l>
                  <l>To yeeld by Loue, and not for ſlauiſh feare,</l>
                  <l>Which makes but temporiſing, and doth beare</l>
                  <l>Two faces in one hood: Therefore deare Sir</l>
                  <l>Be rul'd by mee, and worke no further ſtirre.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come <hi>Paſquill</hi> I will talke with thee: For theſe</l>
                  <l>Doe not my humour nor my fancy pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>What Councell doſt thou giue, what ſhall be donne</l>
                  <l>To worke the good of this Imperiall Sonne?</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquill.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who I? of all the world you wrong me more</l>
                  <l>To aske Aduiſe of me: Why? I haue ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of ſtranger Newes! I muſt proclaime a troth,</l>
                  <l>Which Vncompeld I would bee very loth.</l>
                  <l>I am to tell you Wonders, Prodegies,</l>
                  <l>Inuectiues, Satyres, Rimes, and propheſies,</l>
                  <l>There's not a Worde of mine, but muſt affright</l>
                  <l>Ill tuned Songs by day, ſlumbers by night,</l>
                  <l>Affrighting Starres, and Apparitions,</l>
                  <l>The burning Element with Viſions:</l>
                  <l>All tending ſtill vnto a further matter,</l>
                  <l>Then either Prieſt, or Cardinall dare clatter.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nay, like enough: eu'n Speake and ſpit thy gall,</l>
                  <l>I am reſolu'd, and meane to heare it all:</l>
                  <l>When that the worſt is paſt then better ſure</l>
                  <l>Shall bee propoſde for Patience to endure.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:14579:13"/>
               <speaker>Paſquil.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why this it is to ſtirre a ſleeping Dogge:</l>
                  <l>I all this time lay like a ſenceleſſe Logge,</l>
                  <l>But ſeeing now I vtter muſt my minde,</l>
                  <l>Blame me not Sir, though I doe proue vnkinde,</l>
                  <l>For ſure the hand vpon <hi>Belſhazers</hi> wall,</l>
                  <l>Did not ſo much, as my Tale muſt appall:</l>
                  <l>That onely knokt the knees, and ſtrooke amaze:</l>
                  <l>This ſunders heart and life! Nay doe not gaze,</l>
                  <l>For though I ſing a Song of vncouth ruth,</l>
                  <l>Yet I doe vowe to anſwer nought but Truth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They are with <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Cardinals</hi> ſo bolde,</l>
                  <l>That all at <hi>Rome</hi> is now for Money ſolde:</l>
                  <l>They talke of Tales in their mad Bedlam fitte,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Nauclerus</hi> and <hi>Platina</hi> hath writte</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt Two and twenty <hi>Popes</hi> of ſeuerall names,</l>
                  <l>Who ſolde to Sathan vnto all their ſhames</l>
                  <l>Their very ſoules for Necromanticke ſpels,</l>
                  <l>Had diuers Magicke skils from ſundry Hels,</l>
                  <l>Working affrighting terrors in the Land,</l>
                  <l>Euen in that place, where <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe doth ſtand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They talke of Inceſt, Murther, actes of Treaſon,</l>
                  <l>Of Sodomitry, and without all reaſon</l>
                  <l>Name fortie ſixe Delinquents in theſe kindes,</l>
                  <l>Biſhops Apoſtolickes to pleaſe their mindes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They Catalogue 'gainſt <hi>Cardinals,</hi> with ſtore</l>
                  <l>Of foule Inuectiues: what would you haue more?</l>
                  <l>There's not a ſinne the Deuill euer bred,</l>
                  <l>But hath the <hi>Cardinals</hi> ſtood in ſome ſted:</l>
                  <l>Nay, they goe further, and a ſemblance make</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Affricks</hi> monſters, As you there doe take</l>
                  <l>Notice of ſtranger Beaſts, then are elſe-where:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14579:14"/> So <hi>Rome</hi> begets ſuch ſinnes, as All doe feare</l>
                  <l>A worſe reuenge, then <hi>Sodome</hi> at the firſt</l>
                  <l>Felt, when in wrath the God of Hoſts them curſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They talke of Antichriſt, of lyes, and wonders,</l>
                  <l>Of Plagues and peſtilence, of ſtormes and thunders,</l>
                  <l>Of miracles, which <hi>Costrus</hi> doth recite,</l>
                  <l>With other Authors, who long ſince did write</l>
                  <l>What ſtrange euents in <hi>Pontificean</hi> Sea</l>
                  <l>Paſſed for currant, as a formall Plea.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They talke of irreligion by the way,</l>
                  <l>Of falſifying Scripture, Nay they ſay</l>
                  <l>There's nothing there but diueliſh Hereſie:</l>
                  <l>And filthy Sciſmes, ſauering Apoſtacie:</l>
                  <l>Adding withall, a Friers deadly hate</l>
                  <l>To burne vp <hi>Magunee,</hi> though it was too late:</l>
                  <l>Onely becauſe Printing was there inuented,</l>
                  <l>Which All the World ſo much hath ſince contented.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They leaue not ſo, but raiſe the dead to ſpeake,</l>
                  <l>With thundring terrors hardned harts to breake.</l>
                  <l>They from the <hi>Sybils</hi> Tales portentous tell</l>
                  <l>Of Antichriſts damnation into Hell,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall be deuaſted, ſet on fier,</l>
                  <l>Pul'd downe to rubbiſh, by thoſe that deſier<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her vtter ruyne, wiſh her pride abated:</l>
                  <l>And this amongſt them all is ofte related.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They forward doe proceed to holy Writ,</l>
                  <l>Which they auerre onely to ayme at it</l>
                  <l>With Character of whoriſh <hi>Babilon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The filthy Strumpet: Thus they caſt vpon</l>
                  <l>Her beauteous face fouleſt aſperſions,</l>
                  <l>Naming her <hi>Ieſabel</hi> by falſe inuerſions.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe they call that man of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14579:14"/> And when ſo er'e to murmure they begin</l>
                  <l>Againſt our Churches flouriſhing, they ſay</l>
                  <l>A fatting Beaſt is kept for ſlaughter day.</l>
                  <l>They roue at Brimſtone, Sulphur, fier and flames,</l>
                  <l>At Sword and Famine, and at ſtranger names,</l>
                  <l>And all for <hi>Romes</hi> demoliſhing: O God!</l>
                  <l>The very naming is a ſcourging rod.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Iohns</hi> Apocalips they forward goe</l>
                  <l>To ſtrange Predictions, and a hundred ſhowe</l>
                  <l>Of our owne Saints and Writers, 'gainſt your Seat,</l>
                  <l>And with our owne rods doe the Carkas beat.</l>
                  <l>Some talke of one <hi>Baptiſta Nazarus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And of a Monke ſurnamed <hi>Lazarus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some of an Abbot <hi>Ioachimus</hi> tell,</l>
                  <l>Who of theſe thinges doth write exceeding well.</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>Paracelſus</hi> name, <hi>Laurentius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theodricke, Merlin,</hi> and <hi>Hieronimus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some of Iohn <hi>Wolfius</hi> and <hi>Grebnerus</hi> ſpeake,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Propheſies with terrors out doe breake.</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>Noſtradamus, Gallus, Reymer,</hi> name,</l>
                  <l>With diuers others, who long ſince defame</l>
                  <l>The glory of our <hi>Rome</hi> and holy <hi>Popes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Seeking to blot out all religious hopes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not thus content, they come to <hi>Hildegard,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Saint and Nun, who ſentence did award</l>
                  <l>To this effecte, that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould purged be</l>
                  <l>By ſword and fier, as ſome Age ſhall ſee.</l>
                  <l>They cite <hi>Matilda</hi> a profeſſed Nunne,</l>
                  <l>Who for her holines ſuch credit wonne</l>
                  <l>She plainly ſaith, that <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be deſtroyed,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe her filth hath all the world annoyed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elizabeth</hi> another Sainct is brought,</l>
                  <l>Who by a ſtranger Propheſie ſo wrought,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:14579:15"/> That very Boyes the Day and time durſt name</l>
                  <l>Of deuaſtation, to your vtter ſhame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Saint <hi>Bridgtt</hi> was a fourth, of fearfull noate,</l>
                  <l>Who in her time cryed out with open throate</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Popes,</hi> 'gainſt
<hi>Rome</hi> and all her glory,</l>
                  <l>And of her Propheſies made a whole Story.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The laſt Saint <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>Siena</hi> was,</l>
                  <l>Who brought as much diſcomfort: For alas</l>
                  <l>She talk'd of nothing, but repent, or die,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Babilon</hi> muſt fall: The God on high</l>
                  <l>Had ſo diſpoſde; and <hi>Rome</hi> was
<hi>Babilon:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I dare no more: and thinke, that what is done</l>
                  <l>You raiſde it vp, as if a darkning Clowde</l>
                  <l>Should threaten rayne, when that the windes belowde.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now out vpon thy foule wide mouth, thy tongue</l>
                  <l>Out-rooted ſhall be, cauſe it is too long:</l>
                  <l>A Myne of Powder ſhall thy body blowe</l>
                  <l>Into the Ayre, and all thy aſhes throwe</l>
                  <l>Into the Sea, that no more memory</l>
                  <l>Be made of this thy rauing extacy:</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Paſquil.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And that were wiſely done, but Sir, take heed,</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Hidras</hi> cut off head ſeauen other breed.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pope.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>And dar'ſt thou ſpeake againe? then let's away:</l>
                  <l>I will not for a greater miſchiefe ſtay:</l>
                  <l>For ſure I ſee, that all the world's delighted</l>
                  <l>To haue Vs thus abuſed, and deſpighted.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <q>
               <p>Terruerant ſatis haec pauidam praeſagia plebem, Sed maiora premunt:</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lucan. lib:</hi> 1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:14579:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
